<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The groans of the poor, the misery of traders, and the calamity of the publick for the spoiling of our money, for the want of our money, and for the loss that will befal the King and the nation, if there be not as much money coined in the room of it, to pay our taxes, drive our trades, pay our rents, and the the poor to buy bread : and an humble proposal to raise four millions of money for His Majesty's and the nation's use / humbly proposed by a faithful servant to His Majesty and the nation, William Hodges.</title>
            <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15586035</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15586035</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1150:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The groans of the poor, the misery of traders, and the calamity of the publick for the spoiling of our money, for the want of our money, and for the loss that will befal the King and the nation, if there be not as much money coined in the room of it, to pay our taxes, drive our trades, pay our rents, and the the poor to buy bread : and an humble proposal to raise four millions of money for His Majesty's and the nation's use / humbly proposed by a faithful servant to His Majesty and the nation, William Hodges.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: William Hodges.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Currency question --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103972:1"/>
            <p>THE Groans of the Poor, THE Miſery of Traders, AND THE Calamity of the Publick.</p>
            <p>For the Spoiling of our <hi>Money;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Want of our <hi>Money;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the Loſs that will befal the <hi>King</hi> and the Nation, if there be not as much Money Coined in the Room of it, to pay our Taxes, drive our Trades, pay our Rents, and the Poor, and to buy Bread.</p>
            <p>AND</p>
            <p>An Humble Propoſal to Raiſe Four Millions of Money for His Majeſty's and the Nation's Uſe.</p>
            <p>Humbly Propoſed by a Faithful Servant to His Majeſty and the Nation,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Hodges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:103972:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103972:2"/>
            <p>THE Providence of our moſt Gracious God having ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me up two Years paſt to fore-ſee the Ruin and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Money, and to Print 600 Sheets, in order to repreſent the ſame, to the two moſt Honourable Honſes of Lords and Commons in Parliament, and an humble Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal to call it in, and have as much new Coined, and that good mill'd Money, and without any charge to the Nation. But that being now too late to repreſent again, Silver and Guinea's having been carried beyond Sea, in ſo great a meaſure that they did once, by reaſon of its ſcarcity, riſe to 6 Shillings 9 Pence <hi>per</hi> Ounce, and the other to 30 Shillings the Piece, and glad we had them. But now, ſince the riſe of the ſame, that other Nations could not find it worth while to carry it away, but inſtead thereof they brought us abundance of our Gold again, and took our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Goods from us, and we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed had our Manufactures bought up faſter than they could be made, they are riſen but to pull down our own Goods. There is a Pamphlet come out, called, <hi>A Letter from a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in</hi> Amſterdam. Wherein he ſtrives to have all our Mony Coined large enough for Strangers to carry away; and if we do not, he tells us, in a threatning way, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that they have gotten away all our Clippings of our Money already, but he ſaith, we had no advance of our Goods by its loſs; and that is true enough; and by the way, I would obſerve, that the littleneſs of our Money did not make the dreadful alteration of Prizes, either in Lands, Goods, or Food, among our ſelves. But though it were worth but half the value, it paid Landlord and Tenant, the King's Tax, and Tradeſmen, and every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to content, but thoſe who were to Ship it away; and not a Penny loſs to any one, if it were not Braſs; and therefore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103972:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the experience of ſeveral Years ſhews, that Poſition of the riſing of our Goods, to follow the lightneſs of our Mony, is a <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e; and for the Riſe of our Goods, in taking home our <hi>Guineas</hi> ſo high, it ſhews two things, firſt they are Shipped away dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, when they were low, and returned to us again when they roſe, and the advance of our Goods to other Nations, is the advantage of <hi>England;</hi> and to hearken to thoſe who in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> tell us, they muſt have our Money, or if not, as the Merchant from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> faith, they will drain us of our Goods, yea, of our Wool. But this is like the threatning of a Hector to a Prodigal Son, that ſpends more than he gets; if your Father will not ſupply you with Money, I will ſeize on your Eſtates. And to prevent this, it may be, ſome fond Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or Mothers, ſupplies them with Money, until they are ruined themſelves: And it may be it is in vain to give any of theſe counſel. But in ſhort, the only way to reclaim a Son, that ſpends a great deal faſter than he gets, is, if it be not too late, to keep him from Money to make away and be cheated of: And in ſhort, I look upon <hi>England</hi> as a Family, and the King and Parliament as Husband and Wife, as King <hi>Charles</hi> hinted at, in one of his Speeches to the Parliament; and I look upon the Nation as the reſt of the Family; and our Expences in Silks, and Wines, and <hi>Flanders</hi> Lace, and foreign things, for Pride, or Exceſs, or at leaſt that might be ſpared, to be near two Millions a Year charges. Now if we will let our own Manufactures be Drugs, for want of Exportation, as they were ſome Years when Money was Shipped away, then we may well be poor. For if our Tin, and Lead, and Cloth, and Serges, and all other Goods, will not bear our Expences, but we muſt ſpend more than we can get, we muſt be poor. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that have the Silver Mines, are ſo, becauſe their Money is gotten away from them. And experience ſhews, our mill'd Money is moſt part gone; and if it were bought up for Twenty or Thirty Years, when Goldſmiths fold it for two Pence in the Pound profit, what will it be when it is worrh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103972:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Twenty <hi>per Cent</hi> carrying away ro ſeveral Nations, and like to be worth Ten or Fifteen <hi>per Cent.</hi> in a few Months to melt down here. For ſo ſoon as our Money was gone, and Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings gone, then Silver roſe to Six Shillings Six Pence <hi>per</hi> Ounce. And indeed, now the very thoughts of our Money being Five Shillings Two Pence the Ounce, hath made our Silver fall; for what Goldſmith would give Six Shillings and Six Pence the Ounce, when his Money is at Five Shillings Two Pence: And by the way, notwithſtanding all the pretences of little Money making Goods riſe, I have known a Goldſmith hath ſold about Thirteen Pound value of Plate, and taken Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Money for it, at about half the weight, and ſo long as it paſſed away he was pleaſed; and ſo was all People with Corn, and all Proviſions: And I do methinks ſee the value of Four or Five Millions of Money, juſt as it were loſt from <hi>England,</hi> that is about one half may be call'd <hi>counterfeit Coin,</hi> and melted down; and that is brave to carry away firſt in Bars or Ingots of Silver, and the other half will, it may be, be taken into the Exchequer, and that will Coin one Million, and of that Million I do expect the <hi>Danes,</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> and <hi>Flemings,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> will get it away in about a Years time, if it be Coined as large as before; and what we muſt have to Trade with God knoweth.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, there's a deal of mill'd Money laid up, which will come out when we have new mill'd Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>Now this is one plauſible Argument or Wheedle; but my Arguments are from Reaſon and Senſe: For if I hear the mill'd Money is gone, and ſee it going this Twenty Years, and feel nor Five Pound of it in Five Thouſand Pound abroad, theſe three Senſes tells me, it is greateſt part gone. Some may be left, I ſuppoſe, for it is a hard Battle where none ſcapeth. But if they hoarded it up before, and ſince Guineas went at Thirty, might have had a gain for 26 Shillings of mill'd Money, if they had parted with it, but would not, then what ſhould move
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103972:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>them now: It may rather be feared that they will keep it more carefully, for fear if that be gone, they ſhall never ſee it again; alſo, if they laid up, as a Friend of mine ſaid he was offered Two Thouſand Pound of Money, lately, on his Bill, whereof Four Hundred Pounds was mill'd, and the reſt other Money, and the one was to put off the other: Then if there be mill'd Money, this Party to be ſure will hoard up all mill'd Money next him. And another thing my Eyes, and Ears, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding tells me, of great Sums of Money that abundance of People will not have now themſelves, and it may be have not theſe 3 or 4 Years kept their Money by them, becauſe they could not get mill'd Money, and ſo have taken Goldſmith's Bills to lye by them, inſtead of Money: And if there be mill'd Money Coined at 5 Shillings 2 Pence the Ounce, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, peradventure here will be near two Millions of Money call'd into Men's hands, that now have only Bank Bills, and Goldſmith's Bills. But I do not apprehend there will be much above a Million of Money Coined now of the large mill'd Money of this Crope. For my Reaſon tells me, that while Money is in other Nations worth Fifteen or Twenty <hi>per Cent.</hi> more than here, ours will be carried away, but none brought here. for the Merchants that plead ſo hard to have our Mony made ſo weighty, as to pay the outlandiſh Bills with, will not be ſo fooliſh as to bring Silver here at 5 Shillings 2 Pence the Ounce, if they can have 6 Shillings in <hi>France,</hi> and ſome other Nations; ſo that I ſuppoſe our Mint will ſtand full again after the old Money is all gone; and then it may be the Comers will ſay, This was the laſt ſhift, as the Fellow ſaid when he had ſold his Shirt: but if Money had been coined at 3 Ounces for 20 Shillings, it would have paid its own charge, if Silver had riſen ſo much; but becauſe this would have been for the publick advantage, and fill'd the Nation full of Money again. But thoſe that Ship away our Money could not have gotten the carrying it away; therefore they will argue againſt it: And indeed, all the Propoſals in the World, would not get
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103972:4"/>our <hi>Guinoas</hi> to have riſen ſo much, if the King, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Occaſions, had been to have the advantage, but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of Money to trade with, and the lucre of Gain, cauſed them to riſe in private hands quickly. And indeed, I ſee not what Money will be left to trade with, or pay the King's Taxes with, except it be <hi>Guineas:</hi> And if half the Taxes in the City and Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> have lain unpaid for want of Silver Money, where will the Money be to pay Six Millions a Year Taxes, when the old Money is called in, or if not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in, either hoarded up, as too good to paſs, or though very good, yet none will take it? And my mind being ſet wholly upon the Glory of God, the proſperity of the King's Majeſty, and theſe Nations, and to prevent, if poſſible, the dreadful Ruin of the Poor, I have, with a ſad and a diſconſolate heart, written theſe Lines, to think what our poor miſerable People in <hi>England</hi> will do, for ſmall <hi>Money</hi> to buy Bread and ſmall poor Proviſions with, when I hear how they are ſerved already, before our <hi>Money</hi> is called in; and how they do grieve at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Money</hi> will not paſs, I think it is ſad. A Friend of mine followed one lately, that bemoaned his Caſe, none would take his <hi>Money</hi> for Victuals; and my Friend over-hearing him mourn over his condition, reſolved to aſſiſt him with better <hi>Money,</hi> though he took his bad, and ſo did give him good Six Pences in the room of it. But I fear it will be of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſepuence to the Poor; and if it were poſſible to have a million of <hi>Money</hi> coined in 3 Months, in Crowns and half Crowns, it would not do for the Poor, becauſe many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them muſt have their <hi>Money</hi> by a Shilling, or Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Pence at a time, or they muſt ſtarve; and how all the poor miſerable Penſioners muſt do, that have but Nine Pence, or One Shilling the Week to Live on, God knows, if they have not that ſort of <hi>Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is one thing more I ſuppoſe, that may weaken the Nation in general, ten times as much, amongſt private Traders, in a Year or two, as all our Money is worth, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103972:5"/>that is the want of <hi>Money</hi> to return; I ſuppoſe, if there was a poſſibility to know the loſs hath been already in <hi>England,</hi> it is near a hundred thouſand Pound: For I ſuppoſe I could name ſeveral that have refuſed, and loſt the taking of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pound a piece, for want of <hi>Money</hi> that could be taken: And this is but the beginning of ſorrow: For if we have but half the <hi>Money,</hi> and ſo but half the Trade, this will be the ruin and deſtruction of a great many Thouſands. I am plain hearted, and write for no private Intereſt; but I fear it will be fatal to the Intereſt of the King and Nation, to call it all in at once, and to have none to ſupply the want of it. Which is almoſt like taking off a poor Man's Cloaths, becauſe they are very bad, and telling him he ſhall have better when the Cloth is ſpun and wove; and if the Man ſtarve in the mean time, who can help that when he is dead. I remember a little time paſt there was an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> to cauſe crackt and broken <hi>Money</hi> to go; and the reaſon was rendred, becauſe People had not <hi>Money</hi> to pay their Taxes. Now I ſuppoſe, that crackt and broken <hi>Money</hi> was not about the two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredth part, and if that could not be ſpared, by the ſame rule it will be a hundred, if not two hundred times worſe for them to raiſe it, if they get none at all; ſeeing, as I remember, the Act ſaid, <hi>They had not money to pay them without it.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do verily believe it had been much better to have call'd in only the half Crowns firſt, and ſeen what we ſhould have had to ſhew of them next <hi>Christmaſs:</hi> and then if we had any thing ſeen for them, then call'd in the Shillings and Six Pences, but got more coined for the Poor's uſe firſt: and alſo by that we had had 3 Arrows to ſhoot, two of our Silver, and one of our Gold. And now if our Silver Arrow be ſhot away, and loſt in the Hedge, we have only our Gold to ſhoot with. I am plain hearted, I love my King and Country; and if I were ſure that one would puniſh me, and the other hang me, if I did know this Calling in of our Money ſo all at once, would ruin the Nation in their Trade, and the King in his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103972:5"/>Taxes to bear the charge of the War; and ſo we ſhould be fool'd into the hands of the <hi>French</hi> at laſt. I would tell our King and Nation of it plainly, and ſo look to it in time; and not ſpare charges to tell them; and I would take what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they pleaſe to give me for my pains, with as much Love to them, and ten times more than ſome that they pay largely, and helps to cheat and couzen them both, the more is the pity.</p>
            <p>And now I think of that, it makes me think of three things at once.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The prodigious Riches that theſe Nations hath loſt, or fool'd away, into the Hands of the <hi>French,</hi> on the one hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And the Millions of Money that the Admiralty, or Navy-Office, hath paid away in the Sea-Affairs, that could have been ſaved; according as one of the Commiſſioners of the Navy hath Stated the Caſe himſelf. And if that be but Four Millions charge extraordinary, it is ſomething: And if His Majeſty hath been cheated of near a Million, in ſeveral ways; and if the <hi>French</hi> has gotten near a hundred Men of War; and the many and many hundreds of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants loſt but 10 Millions of Riches from us, there will be 14 Millions of difference that way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the <hi>French</hi> K. has raiſed his Money (as that he hath done ſeveral Years I think a full third part) then if he had 20 Millions of <hi>Sterling</hi> in his Countrey before, it is now Twenty Six Millions: and if we had 10 Millions, and call in Five of it, we ſhall not have much above half what we had, and that will be but about a fifth part what he hath, at that rate; and how great a need of Money we need to return in <hi>England,</hi> to bear our Expences.</p>
            <p>I have calculated in ſome Pages following, after my Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal for the raiſing of Four Millions of Money in Bills, which I do believe would be exceedingly to the profit and advantage of <hi>England;</hi> and we muſt have Money, or Money-worth, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103972:6"/>Trade with in <hi>England,</hi> unleſs we will ſtarve; and we muſt defend our ſelves againſt the <hi>French,</hi> if we had not a Penny of Money left; and if we are as a Ship in a Storm, that we muſt throw over-board a great deal of our Goods, yet we ſhould keep our Money in till the laſt; and as the old Poet ſaid,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Save but the Hull, the Maſter, and the men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And we may live to ſcour the Seas agen.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And now to draw a Conſideration: If it be a great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the <hi>French</hi> to raiſe his Money, it muſt be a great loſs to us to keep ours ſo low; and I find all the Arguments uſed here, center in this, it muſt be large to carry away: but to every Million of Money carried away, if we loſe the Return of 30 Millions, and the gains of near 4 Millions every Year, it is ſad. But the <hi>French</hi> know how to keep their Money better, and to keep their Mint going; and if there be not profit to Coin Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſeven Years experience in <hi>England</hi> will tell us, there ſhall be none Coined; and they ſay, <hi>That no Knowledge is like Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember a Story I have read of a King in <hi>France,</hi> in old time, who was conſulting with his wiſe Men, how he ſhould get into ſuch a Countrey to take it. But a Fool was among them, and he ſhot his Bolt, and ſaid, <hi>He adviſed them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, how to get out again.</hi> So many conſult how to get away our Money from us; but I would Conſult how we ſhall have any again; and alſo what we ſhall do without it in Trade; and what the King will do without it in Taxes.</p>
            <p>But I would Propoſe a way to raiſe Four millions of Mony, to aſſiſt the King and Nation, and to call in the Clipp'd and bad Mony, without the loſs of Forty, or a hundred Pound a Man, to make the Mony good, and that with little Charge, for three or four Years. For indeed, the Return of the ſaid
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103972:6"/>Four Millions of Money, will in ſome meaſure, help out with the ſudden Calling in of ſo great a part of the Money of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>And it is well known to multitudes, what vaſt quantities of <hi>Bills</hi> have been given out in payment upon <hi>Loans,</hi> that the King, it may be, payeth <hi>Seven per Cent.</hi> for the Money: And it may be, if theſe <hi>Bills</hi> come to a Tradeſman's hand that needeth <hi>ready money,</hi> then he may loſe 10 or 12 <hi>per Cent.</hi> by his <hi>Bills;</hi> and if he uſe the King well, and ſell him cheap, it may be he gets nothing the firſt time; and it may be next will have a higher price. But if he have ſo much profit, as to loſe 10 or 12 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and get well, then the King pays 20 <hi>per Cent. Interest</hi> in buying and paying, and that is more than He needeth. Whereas theſe <hi>Bills</hi> will be <hi>ready money</hi> to the King and the Subject; if the Subject do reſerve it, he can pay it away preſently to the full value; and while it lyeth by, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing coming alſo of Intereſt. And as to the Expedient of Propoſals to ſecure the <hi>Bills</hi> from ever being counterfeited, <hi>That none ſhall be forced to take them of a Stranger;</hi> that will effectually prevent all Cheats: And if a man is one I know and truſt, that brings me ſuch Bills, I can eaſily Judge if it be a true one: But if not, he is liable to find out who he had it of, and I give him a Receipt for ſo much <hi>money</hi> receiv'd, by ſuch a <hi>Bill,</hi> of ſuch a mark, <hi>A, B,</hi> or <hi>C,</hi> and ſuch a Number: And if ever the <hi>Bill</hi> ſhould be fonnd to be falſe, returning his.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103972:7"/>
               <hi>Bill,</hi> I command the <hi>money</hi> of him, and if he owed it me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he can but owe it ſtill. But however, there will be no great danger; for it may be the <hi>Bill</hi> may paſs through ſeveral hands, before it came to me, and they having every man ſet their Names to the <hi>Bill,</hi> as aforeſaid. And the <hi>Bills</hi> may be Printed and marked alſo, as the <hi>Bank-Bills</hi> are; and would be the way to Raiſe <hi>Four millions of money in three months time for his Majeſty's uſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it might be the way to <hi>Call in</hi> all the <hi>clipp'd money</hi> alſo, without loſs to any <hi>man</hi> of a Penny, except for Braſs <hi>money:</hi> And every <hi>man</hi> that brings in Fifteen or Twenty Pound of <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver money,</hi> to have a <hi>Bill</hi> given him for the ſame value; and that would paſs away again, as ſo much <hi>ready money to any man that knows him, and be better than Bank-Bills that pay no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as I ſaid, theſe being to have 6 <hi>Pence</hi> the Week for every 50 <hi>Pound,</hi> and the Intereſt to be paid, and the <hi>Bills</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for <hi>new Bills</hi> every. Year, would be beneficial, and of very great advantage for the King and the Subject: And that this may not be ſuppoſed ſtrange or unpracticable, I will lay open my Obſervation of the way of Trade and Payment, as I have obſerved for ſome Years, and it is this.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe there hath been in Goldſmith's <hi>Bills,</hi> and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant's <hi>Bills,</hi> near two <hi>millions of money</hi> going; ſo that I have ſeen the humour of the Age; that if, one went to a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith with a Bill of two or three hundred Pound to be paid, they would tranſport him, it may be, with Bills from Shop to Shop, and exchange Bills at every one of them, for ſeveral Shops, ſo that if one in ten could ſpare <hi>money,</hi> it would ſerve, and the <hi>Bills</hi> were paid. But by that trick, I being once or twice ſo ſerved, I learned to conſider of it more afterwards; and alſo to meditate on the nature of their Trade, how they could pay 6 <hi>per Cent. ready money,</hi> and the Law allows them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103972:8"/>to take no more, and yet they get Eſtates, but then I conſidered, many men for ſome Years, it may be, ſince <hi>money</hi> hath been ſo bad, hath rather choſen to take Goldſmith's Notes; and theſe Sums, as I ſaid, of <hi>Paper-money</hi> among the Goldſmiths, being modeſtly computed at two <hi>millions</hi> of <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> the Intereſt is a hundred and twenty thouſand Pound a Year, clear profit, among them. And I ſuppoſe, now the <hi>Bank</hi> may have a <hi>million,</hi> or <hi>fifteen hundred thouſand Pound in Bills;</hi> and theſe <hi>Bills</hi> paſs more current than <hi>Guinea's,</hi> or our white <hi>money:</hi> And indeed, it may be, one Goldſmith's Boy's hand ſhall go for Bills of ſeveral Sums, for <hi>Forty Thouſand pound,</hi> ſome of them <hi>two hundred,</hi> or <hi>five hundred pound</hi> a piece to one man.</p>
            <p>And I have ſeen ſuch ſtriving for <hi>Goldſmith's Bills,</hi> and <hi>Bank-Bills</hi> of late, makes men to conclude, it would be extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary uſeful to have the <hi>four millions of Bills raiſed,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and that eſpecially, to ſupply our want of <hi>money</hi> now the Old is called in.</p>
            <p>For though the <hi>old money</hi> was exceeding bad, yet it ſerved to Trade with, and go to <hi>market:</hi> And as many uſe to ſay, <hi>If it was Leather, if it would paſs, it would ſerve.</hi> But I do verily think, there will be exceeding great need to diſpence the going of all <hi>Shillings</hi> and <hi>Six-pences,</hi> that are not clipped within the Ring, for poor People in City and Country, to have <hi>money</hi> to buy their Bread with. And in my Opinion, the refuſal of ſuch <hi>money</hi> as is not clipped, either <hi>Shillings,</hi> or <hi>half Crowns,</hi> is a grievous Affliction that People put upon themſelves, and on others. For there muſt be <hi>money</hi> to change, or if not, farewel all the <hi>markets</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and ſarewel great part of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers of ſmall Wares, and Victuallers and Chandlers. For in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Suedeland,</hi> where they ſtrive to have in <hi>Bank Dollars,</hi> and our <hi>Crown pieces,</hi> for their great Payments, they do take care to furniſh the People with other <hi>money</hi> to Trade with, that is not ready to carry away; yet I ſay, God ſorbid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103972:8"/>we ſhould have ſuch mix'd baſe <hi>money</hi> as abundance of <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh-money</hi> is; yet we muſt have abundance of ſmall <hi>money,</hi> or the Poor may ſtarve themſelves for want of <hi>money</hi> to go to <hi>market</hi> with.</p>
            <p>And for our <hi>new money,</hi> if it be Coined with ſpeed, it muſt follow by conſequence, it muſt be Coined in <hi>Crown pieces,</hi> and <hi>half Crowns:</hi> and it is my real thoughts that the firſt half Years Coinage will be quickly melted down, or carried away: For if Silver be fallen on the very hopes of it, a <hi>Shilling an Ounce,</hi> when there is not a Supply from abroad for the Goldſmiths, nor the Mint, then I do judge it will keep down while that <hi>money</hi> laſteth. And I do preſume, That all the Laws that have been made this three hundred Years, could never prevent it.</p>
            <p>For now Cheating the King and Nation is at a full growth almoſt; and if the fear of Death, and real Execution of ſome, could not prevent Clipping and Coining, where there muſt of neceſſity be ſeveral Conſederates that have the knowledge of it; How much eaſier will it be to melt it down, where one man can melt down a <hi>thouſand pound</hi> of it, and neither Wiſe nor Servant ever know of it: And if the ſame man ſhould accuſe himſelf, he would be judged a mad man; and ſo long as there is profit to carry it away, it lies in ſo little room, that it will be carried away if the Laws were Death and Forſeiture of Goods, if catched; as it is in <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Prieſt to tell them the great danger of breaking the King's Laws, as they will pretend it may be <hi>Damnation</hi> in their own Cauſe. But for the Cauſe of the King and Country, the King's Officers, the King's Souldiers, and the Fatherly-Prieſt, will all help away the <hi>money</hi> in deſpite of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for a few <hi>Dollars.</hi> And if they, or any Nation in the World, out-does us, either in Arts, or Parts, or Skill, or Will, to cheat their King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, I am deceived, let who will be paid moſt plentiſully to the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103972:9"/>
            <p> And this I muſt ſay further, if when our <hi>money</hi> was worth but <hi>two pence the Ounce</hi> melting down, and <hi>ſix pence in the pound</hi> carrying away, it was done both for ſome Years then, now it hath been carried away, or melted down ſo, to be ſo ſcarce, none appearing: and they have taken our Goods of late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>money;</hi> and all our Manufactures in <hi>England,</hi> hath had the greateſt Trade for Tranſportation this Year, that it may be hath been this <hi>twenty</hi> Years; and our Goods riſen, becauſe they ſend back our <hi>Guineas</hi> for them alſo; then by the ſame Rule, if our <hi>Guineas</hi> fall, or our Silver, worth carrying away, our Goods may be left in our hands for Drugs, as before, and our <hi>money</hi> carried away; and all that can be ſaid to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I fancy, is only to endeavour to blind the Nation. For indeed ſince our <hi>mill'd money</hi> is gone, and the Clippings of the old melted down and gon, and Silver did riſe to <hi>ſeven Shillings</hi> the Ounce, there was no likely way how to have Silver cheap. For all the melting Goldſmiths in City and Country, to be ſupplied with, and for all Merchants to Ship off, but by having <hi>large mill'd money</hi> enough to carry away. But here will be this comfort, that it will be ſeen in a Year or two how it is gone, if it goeth, though not how it goeth away. And then if we have hardly <hi>money</hi> to Trade with, the King and Parliament can then alter the Coinage to ſuch a ſtate, as will ſtay with us, and relieve us again.</p>
            <p>For I do find it was made leſs and leſs in ſeveral Ages, as about the Years and Times following.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1275. K. <hi>Edward</hi> I. A pound weight was</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1353. <hi>Edw.</hi> III. A pound of Silver</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>05</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1422. <hi>Henry</hi> V. A pound of Silver</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1455. <hi>Henry</hi> VI. A pound of Silver</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103972:9"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1509. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. A pound of Silver</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>05</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1550. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. A pound of Silver</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1562. Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> A pound was</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>02</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>So that in the firſt two hundred Years it did riſe from a <hi>penny</hi> to <hi>two pence farthing;</hi> that is, from <hi>twenty pence</hi> the ounce, to <hi>three Shillings and two pence</hi> the ounce; and then in 50 Years from King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. unto the beginning of Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Reign, it riſe fully a third part more; and ſhe eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it to be at <hi>ſixty two pence</hi> the ounce, and there it hath ſtaid ever ſince; but that is above a hundred and thirty Years; and if it riſe a third part in fifty Years, it may riſe another third part from her time to ſome few Years hence: And in thoſe former Days they did find, That all the Laws they could make, could not keep their Money, until they made it leſs.</p>
            <p>And Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that moſt Excellent Governeſs of it all, made it leaſt of all; and after ſhe made the Money leſs, if the Exchequer Accounts be Examined, it will be found the Cuſtoms brought in three times the valve to the Crown. And they that tell us, Money of a third part leſs weight, if good <hi>mill'd ſilver Money</hi> will not pay a <hi>Foreign Bill,</hi> as well as all our own Money, that is not worth ten Shillings in the pound, would pay our <hi>Engliſh Bills,</hi> and all the Lords and Commons in <hi>England</hi> their Rent, do either ſeem to ſay, the Foreigners muſt be better provided for than they, or in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Foreigners do not pay away the Money again in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo do blind the Nations Eyes: For if they pay it away again in <hi>England,</hi> all Mankind muſt ſay, That which ſerves the King and the Nation, would ſerve them, if they paid it away here, to either King or Country. And therefore we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103972:10"/>do, indeed, need to watch all our Ports more ſecurely: And if we do, it can go in the Ceiling of Ships, or twenty odd places, where none ſhall find it.</p>
            <p>I remember an Acquaintance of mine told me ſome Years paſt, He had a parcel of Money in the Ship, and he knew not of its coming on Board; and the Party that owed it was ſent for out of the Ship, upon ſome other account, and he told him where his Money was, and deſired him to deliver it to ſuch a one in <hi>Holland;</hi> and when he came there, the Owner of the Money was got over in another Veſſel, but would not pay my Friend for taking care of his Money; and my Friend had him before the Magiſtrates, and for ten Groats charge his Cauſe was heard, and they made the Man pay him five Pound for bringing over his Money. Now this they did to encourage him.</p>
            <p>But this I will ſay, we had need to keep our Money with Care, for indeed our charge is near twelve times more, this laſt Seven Years, than any ſeven Years of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was. For though the <hi>Spaniſh Armada</hi> was near 128 Ships of War, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> but ſmall Ships, yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did not run away from them; but like <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> at them, and fought them as they could, and with their Fire-ſhips di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided them, and broak their Fleet, broak their Voyage, and their Hearts alſo.</p>
            <p>And if we have twelve times the charge, and that we muſt of neceſſity have, to defend our ſelves, and offend our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, unleſs we would do as the poor miſerable <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> did, ſave their Money and loſe their City to the <hi>Turks:</hi> And we have an Enemy to deal with, more powerful, and a greater Plague to <hi>Christians,</hi> than the <hi>Turks</hi> have been theſe 20 Years, and muſt defend our ſelves. And bleſſed be God, the Parliament and Nation are ſo ready to raiſe Money for to defend our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:103972:10"/>
            <p> But I ſay, that great Charge, requires twelve times more Trade than was in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, to help to carry on the War, and that Trade requires ten times more Money to carry it on, then was in her time: And our <hi>Cuſtom-houſe-Books</hi> will manifeſt, we have twelve times more Trade; and if our Money be not twelve times as much, our Payments muſt be longer, before we pay one the other; and that is ſad, if it ſhould ſo fall out, that we have not plenty of Money: For the very Poſtage of our Letters, comes to more profit to the Crown, than all her Cuſtoms did, before ſhe ſettled Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney at the higheſt value. And we muſt have Money to carry on our Trade, and pay our Taxes.</p>
            <p>And how can the greateſt part of our Silver-Money be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red now altogether, except a ſpeedy care be taken to have a ſupply of new to fill it up; and that it be not carried away, and melted down; for if it ſhould, it may be fatal to the Poor, fatal to the Traders, and fatal in the want of it to pay in our Taxes; and if I compute aright, we have about a hundred thouſand Houſes within the <hi>Bills of Mortality;</hi> and ſuppoſe one with another, at 10 <hi>l.</hi> the Year a Houſe, is a <hi>million</hi> the Year Rent; and ſuppoſe all manner of Charges whatever, ſpent within the ſaid Bills, be nine times as much, is nine <hi>Millions</hi> more, that is ten <hi>Millions</hi> the Year Expences: Or, ſuppoſe there be a <hi>million</hi> of People, and they ſpend 10 <hi>l.</hi> a Year each, Poor and Rich, one with another, is ſtill ten <hi>millions</hi> of Money in a Year; and if all <hi>England</hi> be but ten times as many People, and ſpend ten times as much Money, then that is a hundred <hi>millions</hi> of Money every Year ſpent, in the delicate pretty Iſland of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then if we have but ten millions of Money in <hi>England,</hi> we muſt return it ten times over in a Year, to pay our bare Expences. But then ſuppoſe, that half the Nation conſiſteth of Trades and Merchandiſe, in Cities, and Towns, and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and to get half theſe Expences, which is fifty <hi>Millions</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103972:11"/>the Year, they muſt return this one with another, at leaſt ſix times the Year, to get theſe Expences, and that is three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>millions</hi> return; and the ten <hi>millions</hi> of Money muſt be returned thirty times over, to get their Expences, and five times over to get the other half of the Nations Expences; and the ſaid ten <hi>millions</hi> of Money muſt be paid into the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer likewiſe for Taxes, at leaſt once in two Years; and it may be there it lyeth ſometimes ſeveral Weeks or Months; and therefore I am certain that it will be the Intereſt of the King, and Parliament, and Nation, to have great Plenty of Money, and a great ruin if we have not; and though it may be ſome will ſay, the riſe of Goods will follow the riſe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>It is a pretence; for ſince Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Days, all ſorts of Goods, and all ſorts of Proviſions, and Servants, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers Wages is riſen near three times dearer, though Money hath been at the ſame. For as the Nation increaſeth in Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and Trade, and Riches, yet Corn, Food and Cloaths will riſe, and Wages muſt riſe; and therefore they that argue to have our Money carried away, argue aright to have our Goods fall; for if our Money be gone away, our Goods will be Drugs, and muſt fall; and if we be Poor, we may have Goods cheap; and therefore in other Countries, where they have little Money, they live cheap. But I never knew any Man in my life, go there to live, to get Money, where things are ſo cheap.</p>
            <p>And now I think of our Guinea's riſing; it hath been one of the greateſt advantage the Nation hath had in Trade this War, that I do know of; for the bringing over them of a ſuddain, hath cauſed ſuch a riſe in our own Manufactury. And one thing I would obſerve, that it may be ſome will argue from the Goods are riſen, but that is our great loſs at Sea, and our ſcarcity of them. But for our <hi>Hamborough</hi> Goods, if they are riſen ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Goods carried over there, and to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103972:11"/>the Eaſt parts, is ſome of it riſen, to my knowledge, 30 <hi>per Cent.</hi> So that if they take our Goods, as they muſt do before our Money be ready for them, we ſhall gain more Profit to the Nation by the riſe of our Goods 5 or 10 <hi>per</hi> Cent. extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, beſides what they raiſe theirs. And therefore I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce that Guineas were ſettled at Thirty Shillings the piece, and a hundred thouſand would be quickly Coined into half Guineas for Change for poor People, and poor Traders uſe: And then if our Silver-money ſhould be carried away faſter and ſooner than we are aware of, we ſhould have ſome Gold to Trade with, and to pay the King's Taxes: And it is pity they have not been paid current in Payment to poor Seamen, rather than that baſe, ſcandalous, braſs, counterfeit and clipt Money that hath been paid to them for a conſiderable time. And indeed, it is one of the Riddles of the Age, That the beſt Money is paid into the Taxes, and ſuch horrid bad Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney paid out again to the poor miſerable Seamen, or labouring men.</p>
            <p>But this I would obſerve, That there is not any miſery hardly in the World, but the Seamen come in for a ſhare of, beſides their Sea miſeries; and how the poor Seamen will get off their clipp'd and braſs half Crowns, I know not; they cannot afford to pay them into Taxes again.</p>
            <p>But this by the way, there will be need of <hi>Money</hi> that we may keep, and that will ſerve to pay the poor miſerable People of <hi>England.</hi> A Shilling or two at a time, they muſt buy their Bread with, and their Cheeſe, or courſer Victuals, with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Groat or Six Pence, and it may be a fore Piece of meat for eight Pence; and if our <hi>Money</hi> be all Coined large Crowns, and half Crowns, how muſt they change.</p>
            <p>But I having obſerved all the Books of Coinage I could meet with, do find that the main Arguments pleaded for large mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is, becauſe Strangers will raiſe our Goods; and yet they would blind our Eyes, as if Strangers did not carry away our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103972:12"/>Mony at laſt, and that is againſt Senſe and Reaſon; for if ſtrangers carried not away our Mony: why is not a Crown Piece of the value of three quarters of an Ounce as good for them to pay away here, as a Crown Piece of an Ounce weight: But to ſay no more, but this, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that have the Silver Mines of their own, their Silver being Cheap, is carried away from them, and they are a poor People, and glad to accept of the help of their Neighbours to ſupport them againſt the <hi>French,</hi> who get away their Mony from them, and I am afraid from us alſo many times; and the <hi>French</hi> are ſo cunning, as to raiſe their Mony a quarter part, that none ſhall carry it away from themſelves again; and as it is ſaid in the Goſpel, <hi>The Children of this World are wiſer than the Children of Light.</hi> And this I will ſay on the one hand, that if the Return of Four Millions of mony thereon, thirty heads in a year, gaineth twelve millions; then if we had four millions of mony called in, and but one million of mony Coined in the Room, we looſe the three millions of mony quite, and the profit of the Return of it thirty times in a year, at nine millions of Profit; and whether they will not now be at a cheaper paſs to carry away our mony, than ever; for formerly they gave two Shillings in the pound Profit for mill'd mony, and went from ſhop to ſhop to buy it; and now they will have it at beſt hand; and indeed it may be conſidered; however the Mint will be ſupplied after our old mony is call'd in and melted down, if Silver be but a Grain in an Ounce dearer, before it be Coined, than after, then none will Coin it; but it will be worth four times as much to melt down and carry away, as when it was worth but a Penny an Ounce; and if our Goods fall, becauſe that the ſtrangers carry away our mony, and leave our Goods; then it may be queſtioned how our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation muſt pay their Rents better, or Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es better, when they have but a quarter of the mony they uſe to have, and leſs Prices for their Goods: And if I do not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtand
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103972:12"/>the World in the time of K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. when the Parliament-Money was called in then, in ſome time after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Farms in <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and ſeveral other parts, did fall off their Rents, near a quarter part; and what hath been, may be; but in ſhort, our <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Merchants, that Trade to <hi>West India</hi>'s, knows that they are forced to ſupply our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, moſt of them with Goods, and take Goods again; but thoſe Merchants that Tranſport away our Money knows, If they cannot get our Money to be Coined ſo large as to pull down the price of melted Silver, they ſhall be at a loſs, how to ſend away Silver; and it may be, if I were a covetous <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Merchant, I would ſtrive all I could, that our Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Money ſhould be ſo large, as that ten thouſand pound of that ſhould ſerve to go as far as twelve thouſand pound in mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Silver; and ſo my Goods would coſt me cheaper indeed, but the Nation loſe the return of this ten thouſand Pound for ever.</p>
            <p>And I am of Opinion, That if our Money get over beyond Sea, if it be but as far as <hi>Holland,</hi> it will never come back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, except it riſe, as doth our Guineas, and then it would come again. And if our Guineas ſhould fall, they would quickly ſtep over there again, and they would ſerve us by our Money, as they do by our Corn; when it is plenty carry it away, and when it is twice the price, bring it us again; when they can double their Money. And in ſhort, I fear all the Money we ſhall Coin this nine Months, will be little enough to melt down and carry away; and that doth make me fear, the next Years miſery, to have hardly any Money, whereas were it ſo ordered, as to call in our old Money by degrees, and to Coin other between the weight of the old, that is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two Ounces to the Pound, and the mill'd of Four Ounces, and as much to be conſtantly Coined, as is taken in the Nation, would have the ſame value of <hi>Money</hi> ſtill, and half of good again; and if it be true that <hi>Money</hi> is our Sinews of War, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103972:13"/>cutting off half the Sinews in a body at once, muſt weaken it, and I fear will need great care for healing and ſtrengthening Plaiſters. And in ſhort, if other Ages, as they grew wiſer and wiſer, and ſaw how their <hi>Money</hi> was carried away, made it leſs, that they might keep it, then we may be admired at, if there be not more care taken to have plenty now, and to keep it, than to have but a little, and ſuch as is fit to ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to all parts of the World. And I ſuppoſe, if the <hi>French</hi> King were to wiſh us a miſchief with a witneſs, he would wiſh our <hi>Money</hi> ſpent, and gone from among us, and our Seamen ruined; and that there might for time to come, be ſuch <hi>Men</hi> imployed in the managing of our Sea-Affairs, as might let our <hi>Merchandize</hi> be fooled into his hand; and in the mean time, to let the King and Nation be cheated dreadfully at home, and they ſmuggle it up all at laſt. But I will ſay no more but only this, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord give us wiſdom in all things.</hi> And alſo, the Lord in mercy bleſs our moſt Gracious and Valiant Majeſty, K. <hi>William,</hi> and the two moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proposal">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:103972:13"/>
            <argument>
               <p>This following Paper was delivered to the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in the Year of our Lord 1693.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>
               <hi>An Humble Propoſal to their Moſt Excellent Majeſties King</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and Queen</hi> MARY, <hi>and to the two moſt Honourable Houſes, the</hi> Lords <hi>and</hi> Commons <hi>aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly ſheweth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. FIRST, How our Trading Money may be made one fourth part better than now, we uſually receive One Hundred and twelve Pounds ten Shilling, weighing down One Hundred and Fifty Pounds of our Old Money.</p>
            <p n="2">II. How we may have five or ſix millions of Money Comed in three or four Years time to the Joy of our Hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">III. How we may keep the ſaid Money when we have it, and not have it melted down, or carried away.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. How we may call in a Hundred Thouſand Pounds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth of Crackt and broken Money, and have new coin'd without any Loſs or Charge.</p>
            <p n="5">V. How to have plenty of Silver brought into <hi>England</hi> every Year, whereby the Mint will be always ſupplied.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. How to have near a Million of Goods tranſported more every year in time of Peace and War than uſual.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. How much the Ages to come will have cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, as well as the preſent time, if we have plenty of Mill'd Money.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. If Care be not taken in time to have a ſupply of good Mill'd Money that we may keep, how miſerable bad all our trading Money will be, even the worſt in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. How great a happineſs to the Nation in Trade, the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103972:14"/>Coining of ſix or ſeven Millions of Mill'd-Money will be, if it be ſo we can but keep it among our ſelves, and the Reaſons are as follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. It may be obſerved by all that Receive Money for their Majeſties, or for themſelves, either from the Goldſmiths, or in way of Trade, That the moſt of the Money that we receive is Old Money, ſome broken, and a great deal clipt, and ſome half worn out, very ſeldom our Mill'd Money coming to Hand in Payments that we Receive: And if any will take the pains to weigh 10 <hi>l.</hi> of Mill'd Money with 15 <hi>l.</hi> of the Old, that 10 <hi>l.</hi> of Mill'd Money ſhall weigh down the 15 <hi>l.</hi> of the Old, and that 100 <hi>l.</hi> of mill'd money ſhall weigh down 150 <hi>l.</hi> of the Old, if taken as it is received, but ſometimes 4 <hi>l.</hi> of mill'd Money ſhall weigh down 7 <hi>l.</hi> of the Old: And there being ſo many Clippers continually a clipping of our old Money, it will be worſe and worſe every Year; and there being ſo many Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths, or Silver-Wire-Drawers, or others concerned in mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down out New-money, and ſo many outlandiſh men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the buying up, and carrying away of our Old mill'd money, we are like to have leſs and leſs of it for time to come, if ſome way be not found out for to prevent it, and while it is ſo weighty, and at no higher price, no Law can hinder its being melted down, or carried away, except Angels would be at the trouble to execute them; for men that melt it down can do it, and none ſee them; and they that carry it away, can hide it as none find it, and they will never accuſe themſelves, except they are diſtracted: And the reaſon why we have ſo little of the mill'd, and do keep their Old is, becauſe one is too good to keep, and the other too bad to carry away: And we have not half enough of the Old neither; and therefore that which I would propoſe is, That we might have a new Coinage that might be better by a quarter part than our Old; that is, that 112 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> of the New might
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103972:14"/>weigh down 150 <hi>l.</hi> of the Old money; and that the ſaid 112 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> ſhould weigh down 100 <hi>l.</hi> of our mill'd money that now we have; and in doing ſo, we ſhould have plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of good Money quickly, a full fourth part better than what we have, and have the Mint kept in continual ſupply with Silver; ſo that they ſhould never need to ſit ſtill ten days in a Year, and the profit of 400000 <hi>l.</hi> of that money would call in a 100000 <hi>l.</hi> of Crackt and broken money: And it might be ſo ordered, That the Goldſmiths ſhould have one and a half preſent for carrying in a continual ſupply of money, and not to let any lie in the mint above a month or five weeks; ſo that they ſhould return their money ten times every Year, and that would be fifteen in the Hundred in a Year; and for the Coinage there might be one <hi>per Cent.</hi> more or leſs allowed for Coinage, and ſo there can never want Silver nor. Coiners: And for the other ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> to go the firſt 4 or 500000 <hi>l</hi> to call in as I ſaid, a 100000 <hi>l.</hi> of of Crackt Money, and the profit of thereſt, and there might be a Million more Coined in every Year. I would humbly propoſe that there might be 3 or 400000 <hi>l.</hi> worth of crackt and broken, and decayed Money called in every Year, and the profit of the new Coinage will bear the loſs of the old, for it cannot be ſuppoſed that there can be leſs than fifteen hundred thouſand, or two millions of money Coined every Year, if the Mint be kept in a continual ſupply, as it will, if there be one and a half, or ſo allowed to bring in Silver, and the Coiners paid as beforeſaid; and if Silver Riſe, then the more Silver Riſes, the leſs to go towards the calling in Crackt money, ſo that it can never riſe ſo high, but there would be ſome overplus, and the higher Silver riſes, the more plenty we ſhould have brought in: And indeed it may be ſuppoſed our Guineas going at about 22 <hi>s.</hi> at <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> makes us keep them unmelted, and alſo in <hi>England,</hi> and if the Crown-pieces has riſen as much in proportion as the
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103972:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103972:15"/>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:103972:16"/>Guineas, they would have been preſerved: Alſo if every twenty Shillings had gone for a Guinea, and if every Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea were ſettled at 23 <hi>s.</hi> and our Old 20 Shilling pieces at 25 <hi>s.</hi> and the Old 22 <hi>s.</hi> at 27 <hi>s.</hi> they would be daily return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>England</hi> again, if they are not melted down: For it is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that the <hi>Jews</hi> will bring over our Money again, if they get but four or Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> by it. And indeed our mill'd money having been ſo good that ſtrangers for ſome Years have gone from Shop to Shop to buy it up, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away: And if they could not have gotten that, they would rather have bought Goods, which they might have had hopes to get by, but would never have carried our old money to loſe by: And it hath been judged that for ſome years, in times of Peace, we had 800000, or a million of Goods from <hi>France,</hi> in a Year more than they had of us; whereas if our money had not been ſo good, they might have been glad to have taken our Goods, as we did theirs; or if not, Let them have kept their Goods, and we kept our money ſtill, and by that means, and the <hi>Sweeds,</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> and others, we might have tranſported away ſeveral Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of Thouſands a Pounds-worth of Goods in a Year more than we have done: And indeed, if we conſider how great a loſs it is to us to have our own money ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, there is but few can imagine: For firſt, the moſt money we receive now is old money, Coined Fifty or a Hundred Years paſt; and our Trade is double now that it was then, as by the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe</hi> Books will appear: And if our money is no more than what we had, then our Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt be twice ſo long by Conſequence: And indeed every million of money carried out of <hi>England,</hi> is the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of twenty or thirty millions of Return, and the loſs of two or three millions gaining among the Nation. As for Example: mony among Tradeſmen commonly returns through thirty or forty Hands every year, and that cannot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103972:16"/>be ſuppoſed, that one with another, they can get leſs than ten <hi>per cent.</hi> and to moſt Lawyers and <hi>Doctors of Phyſick,</hi> and all the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ergy,</hi> and all <hi>Sallaries</hi> under their Majeſties, the money is all gain, and ſo that counting one with another there is but ten <hi>per cent</hi> gotten throughout <hi>England,</hi> by the Return of money, ſo that a millon returned through thirty hands in a Year, gaineth three millions, and the money the ſame at the Years end: And if it beremembred, after cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Parliament-money after 1660, that had been Conining many Years, money was extream ſcarce, and one effect I ſuppoſe of the ſame was the falling of the Rent of Farms in <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and perhaps in moſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys in <hi>England,</hi> and the mill'd Money Coined, ſince ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been melted down, or carried away great part of it, Money is exceeding ſcarce now; whereas, were there ſix or ſeven millions of mill'd money Coined, as might be, in Three or Four Years, that we might keep when we had it, we might find the ſweetneſs of it quickly, and alſo our Children after us: And indeed it cannot be ſuppoſed in Reaſon, but that the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and within the Bills of mortallity, ſpend as much in One year, as is in Ready money in <hi>England,</hi> and the reſt of the Cities, and the Nation in General ſpend it five times over, and yet never a Penny the leſs at the Years end, except it be melted down, or carried away; and indeed the expence of money is the increaſe of Trade, and the Return of money is the ſupport of Expence and Gain; for there are many Thouſands that ſpend a hundred Pound each for many years, that never were worth a hundred Pound a piece in their Lives; and the Return of money being their ſupport; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers getting by them, and ſo the money of <hi>England</hi> being returned forty times over in a Year, or fifty times, that is, through forty or fifty hands, gaineth the value of it five or ſix times over, and every body lives by another; and indeed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103972:17"/>it may be ſuppoſed, that there is as much money owing in <hi>England,</hi> between Tennants and Landlords, Tradeſmen and merchants, and Goldſmiths, and every ſort of men, as twenty times the money in <hi>England</hi> cometh to, there being few men but have twenty times more owing to them, than they have ready money; and if Care be not taken that we may have money that will ſtay with us, I fear we ſhall be like men in Conſumptions: For let men feed what they will, if it ſtayeth not in their Bodies, they cannot be Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: And let us Coin what we will, if we keep it not, we ſhall not grow very rich: For money is ſo great a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial, it is like Blood in the Veins that Circulates from the Heart to Head and Feet, and every member, and the Body receiveth Life and Vigour thereby, and Nouriſhment, and every member the better for it, and the Blood remains ſtill: And ſo is money in Trade in ſuch a Nation as ours; and we have generally the beſt Goods in the World to ſend out into other Nations our <hi>Tinn,</hi> and <hi>Lead,</hi> and <hi>Woollen-Cloth,</hi> and <hi>Serges,</hi> and other <hi>Woollen Manufactory,</hi> and divers others Goods to fetch in Goods enough, and money alſo, if we did not let other Nations carry away our good mill'd money. And indeed, another loſs is the melting of it down: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there is a very great Error, that many Victuallers, Tradeſmen, and others, have forty or fifty, or a hundred Pound in Plate and Rings by them, which never ſaw half ſo much money together of their own in ſeven Years; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very hundred Pound ſo lying dead and uncoined, doth loſe its being returned through 40 Hands in a Year, which is the loſs of the Return of 4000 <hi>l.</hi> and the loſs of gaining 2 or 300 <hi>l.</hi> among all them it would be returned to; and ſome are ſo fooliſh as to let Plate ly in pawn 5 or 6 years, as a Friend of mine hath had 2, or 300 pounds worth ſo left with him in Plate 5 Years for 200 <hi>l.</hi> the intereſt of which is 60 <hi>l.</hi> And how great a loſs is that to the publick, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103972:17"/>to the Party, who if they had ſold the Plate at firſt, had ſaved 60 <hi>l.</hi> And if we conſider how ſad a Condition the next Age will be in, if there be not ſome Care taken to leave them better money than our Old money, that is too light by 50 in 150 <hi>l.</hi> And if we do not take Care, it will be leſs, ſo many hundreds being concerned in the Clipping-Trade: And alſo it may be conſidered, That as there is near double the number of Traders now that was fifty years paſt, ſo we do need double the money to carry on the Trade: And if Traders ſhould increaſe a fourth part more in thirty years, we ſhall need three times the money that was Fifty Years paſt; and if there be no money coined but what will be melted down or carried away, they will be then in a far worſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than now we are, which will be bad for Landlords as well as Tennants, and for merchants, as well as Tradeſmen and others.</p>
            <p>But now, If any ſhall ſay the Coining of money one eighth part leſs than our mill'd money would be a Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on us at this time. To that I anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It would be as if a generous Gentleman had uſed to treat <hi>Frenchmen</hi> ſeveral Years, until his Eſtate began ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to decay, and alſo they began to quarrel with him, and others to ſlight him, and his own Family in the mean time began to want that money he had ſpent on others: But however he did conſider in time, and got more good money, and ſpent it in his own Family, and among his Neighbours, and they were all the better for it, and his Father had many a good Treat out of it alſo, and yet the Gentleman waſted none of his Eſtate. The Strangers indeed would complain they could not cheat him as before; but his Real Friends loved him the better: And as the Wife man ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9. 12. <hi>If thou be wiſe, thou ſhalt be wiſe for thy ſelf.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if others complain we are not ſo ready to part with our Silver as before, let them know it is for the Publick Good for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:103972:18"/>time preſent, and for the Ages to come; and if they will be ſo free to us for 30 Years, to bring us ſo much good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as they have gotten from us, then let them complain; but they neither are able, nor willing to reſtore our Money to us again: And indeed it is no reaſon the preſent Age, or the Age to come, ſhould be beggar'd for a notion to pleaſe ſtrangers; and for our ſelves, our money will be really bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by about 30 <hi>l.</hi> in the hundred than our Old money; if this new Coinage be Eſtabliſhed, and we may with Eaſe call in our broken money, and have five times as much good money in the room of it in a very few Years, and have it Coined all in mill'd Half-Crowns and Crown, whereby it could not be clipt, and would not be mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed down, and the Revenue that is now already for C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ge, may be given Their majeſties for their uſe: And <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any ſhall object that this New Coinage would not be large enough to Tranſport for paying off their Majeſties Forces beyond Sea, and ſo would be a prejudice to their majeſties Affairs abroad.</p>
            <p>Now to that I anſwer. Such an Argument would be no Real Objection againſt this Coinage: For firſt, I do not hear there hath been above ſix or ſeven days work in Coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſeveral months; And were we not better go to work conſtantly to Coin for the uſe of their Majeſties, and the Nation's good here, than to let the mint ly ſtill, and do nothing, becauſe of that?</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> If there is a neceſſity of ſending mill'd money to pay thoſe Forces, it is a ſign that there hath been a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful havock of the mill'd money in times of Peace, if thirty Years Coinage ſhould have ſuch large Wings as to fly away. and not have enough left for that uſe, and not Silver to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the mint neither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> But I ſuppoſe His Majeſty can pay his Forces by Bills of Exchange for Foreign money, as I do preſume he hath done oftentimes before; and ſo that objection makes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103972:18"/>much more againſt the Old mill'd money, than this new propoſed for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If there were plenty of Money Coined, as there might be Two millions every Year, the Return of it would be fifty Millions in a year, and the People would be inabled chearfully to pay their Taxes freely, and the King and People would be all happy in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> And indeed, If I did not think it for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of Their Majeſties and the Nation alſo, I ſhould deſerve ſevere Puniſhment; for there is now at this time a neceſſity for us to defend our ſelves from that Common Plague of the Chriſtian World, the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant, that hath burned more Chriſtian Cities and Towns in his time, than the <hi>Turks</hi> have done this Hundred and Fifty Years: and hath rooted out the Proteſtant Religion more effectually out of his Nation, than all the Bloody Perſecutions did ſince the Reformation. And it is a wonder to me, if any <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> can be ſuch Deviliſh Enemies to their own Religion and Country, as to think, that he that Ruins his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to plague all his Neighbours, and hath ruined the Proteſtant Religion of his own Loving, Faithful Subjects, that he ſhould be kind to us, and eſtabliſh a Proteſtant Church here, is againſt Grace and Reaſon, and common Sence, to think, and therefore Treaſon and Rebellion now looks like to Witchcraft; for as Witches through Malice kill their Neighbour's Children and Cattle, and are miſerable them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at laſt; ſo thoſe who would betray us to the <hi>French,</hi> ſhew their Deſigns to be only Malice from the Devil; for they could not ſecure themſelves to enjoy two-pence of their Eſtates, neither one Pennyworth of their Liberties, nor one Farthing worth of their Religion (if they have any) if the <hi>French</hi> ſhould prevail.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:103972:19"/>
            <p> But we have cauſe to bleſs God <hi>for preſerving theſe Nations,</hi> and <hi>Their moſt Gracious Majeſties,</hi> and that Both of them, and the <hi>Two moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament,</hi> are ſo Unanimous againſt the Common Enemy, and for the Intereſt and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Their Majeſties and theſe Nations, for the Time preſent and to come. Theſe Propoſals are Humbly Preſented by a True Lover of Their Majeſties, and the Proſperity, Liberty and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe Nations; And that in the Safety of theſe Nations I may be Safe, while I Remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Their Majesties Faithful Subject,</hi> VVilliam Hodges.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hermitage,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decem.</hi> 11. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>This Sheet of <hi>Paper</hi> laſt foregoing, was my Thoughts then how our mill'd money was <hi>melted down, or carried away,</hi> and the <hi>other Ruin'd.</hi> But now I find, if I miſtake not, there will be need of near a Million of our old money, if it be Coined as <hi>Large</hi> as the old mill'd money, to be <hi>carried</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> after it is Coined into five hundred thouſand pound; That is, I hear there is three hundred thouſand pound ſubſcribed in <hi>England,</hi> to help carry on their <hi>East India</hi> and <hi>West India</hi> Trade, and they ſend us home ten or twenty thouſand pound of our old money in a Ship: And if they ſend us but two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound, and take two hundred thouſand pound of mill'd money again, that will make up half a Million of the New; And yet I hear there hath been ſome Conſultation how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their <hi>Trade's Increaſe</hi> and <hi>our Trade's Ruin.</hi> But if we <hi>provide them large money,</hi> I fear it will be the <hi>greatest help to them in Trade that ever they had.</hi> Whereas money at 3 <hi>quarters,</hi> the mill'd weight, would be the way to prevent their deſign in a <hi>great meaſure.</hi> But it may be the moſt effectual way to Ruine <hi>their Trade,</hi> would be, if we could <hi>transfer</hi> ſome of our Plagues to them, our Cheatsaud Fxtortioning Ticket-buyers, and ſuch Commanders of Men of War as he that Run away from the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103972:19"/>Privateer lately, when he had about one Man wounded, and let a New Ship be taken coming from <hi>Shoram;</hi> and alſo others that have fool'd away our Ships of War and Merchant Men; and ſend an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiralty and Navy-Board, the one to put in ſuch Officers as will do as aforeſaid, and Run up and down, and do them no good; and if all agree together to Ruin their Seamen and Trade, and to hide an ſmuggle up all Cheating, Cowardize and Roguery; and that all theſe may be ſtill prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and employed until their Trade and Ships be Ruined, and that will do the work. And if any object, and ſay, No Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would ſuffer ſuch to Ruin themſelves, and will by Ignorance or Villany Ruin their Trade, except they were under the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, to be ſmitten with Madneſs and Blindneſs; To that I would anſwer, I ſuppoſe they would not ſuffer them, if they ſaw they were ſo greatly Ruined; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I would not wiſh them ſuch Plagues; But that their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing us in our Trade may be prevented by our hindring them a Supply of Large Money, it being to be feared we have fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home many Droves of their Seamen lately, which will be one great help to them. So begging of the Lord to direct and bleſs our gracious King <hi>William,</hi> and our Loyal Parliament, and theſe Nations; and be the Portion and Bleſſing of them and me, and all my Family; And intreating Pardon for what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſss in this, or any thing wherein I miſtake, I ſubſcribe my ſelf His Moſt Gracious Majeſty King <hi>William</hi>'s Faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the Nations Faithful Friend,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. Hodges.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hermitage-Bridge,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 18. 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
